<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panarmonia, or, The agreement of the people revived, and recommended to the great patrons of the commonwealth and to the sober-minded people of the land in general : humbly presented, with an apology for Christian liberty, to the honourable council of the Army.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55144</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12300517</idno>
  <idno type="VID">59153</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248571629</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22376</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12300517</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59153)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 923:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panarmonia, or, The agreement of the people revived, and recommended to the great patrons of the commonwealth and to the sober-minded people of the land in general : humbly presented, with an apology for Christian liberty, to the honourable council of the Army.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 [i.e. 42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewell Chapman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Greek at head of title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59153:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59153:1"/>
            <p>ΠΑΝΑΠΜΟΝΙΑ.</p>
            <p>OR, THE AGREEMENT OF THE PEOPLE, Revived, and Recommended to the Great PATRONS of the COMMONWEALTH, and to the Sober-minded People of the LAND in general: Humbly presented, with an APOLOGY FOR Christian Liberty, TO THE Honourable Council of the ARMY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Popes-Head-Alley,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59153:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59153:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable and Renowned, &amp;c. and the Council of the ARMY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Fathers, and Gentlemen;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not unknown to you, and other Worthies in Parliament, City and Country, who are now severally and respectively concerned in the great affairs of the Commonwealth, that the gracious and wise Disposer of all things hath once more brought the Man▪ child of the Nations Freedome to the Birth; and is also pleased that it should issue forth from between the feet of this Honourable Parliament. There is nothing wanting (in the judgement of many standers by) to make us happy by such a production, but the sincere and sedulous labour and travel of Mind and Soul, which those should put themselves to, who are by Divine Providence called upon to ennoble themselves by an Off-spring so hopeful, and so much desired as this is. The world's Supreme hath matured and ripened all things to the work; the day declares what is to be done; the night of trouble and opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is somewhat over to you: what remains now, but that you should recall and renew your strengths for the work? that at length you may become partakers of that joy, which will be at the Birth of that Man-child into the world.</p>
            <p>It will not, I hope, be tedious to you to take a view of those cordial salutations and well-wishes conceived in the hearts of some sober and well-minded people in this Country, and intended to be offered to the High Court of Parliament, in the way of an Address and Petition, with subscriptions answerable to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of such an intendment: But the too early rise of another Address, pre-ingaging for its service a great number of those who might have been Subscribers and Promoters of this, (the fate of which, notwithstanding was (if I mistake not) to die without Issue) became a means to the alteration of that course, at first designed for it: So that now it shall content it self to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come publike, (with this Councils leave) only by the help and mediation of a private Owner. I will first present to your sight and perusal the Address it self; and after that, an Appendix, by way of an Inlargement on some particulars in that Address, together with an Apology for Liberty of Conscience. The Address it self followeth in these words:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="address">
                        <pb facs="tcp:59153:3"/>
                        <head>To the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <argument>
                           <p>The humble Address and Petition of several the Justices of Peace, Gentlemen, and others, of the County of <hi>Glocester,</hi> well-affected to the peace and settlement of this Commonwealth.</p>
                        </argument>
                        <p>MAny and wonderful have the Providences of the most High God been in the behalf of this poor, and (as yet) unsetled Nation of ours; even to the amazement (as well as wonder) of the most serious and considerate men: wherein we have had experience of the tempers, inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prevarications of persons interessed in publick Affairs, on the one hand; and of the abundant goodness and mercy of the great and wise Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator of all things, on the other; who hath preserved our State (such as it is) to this day, by raising up of Instruments, from time to time, to assert and vindicate the Peoples Rights against the Incroachments, Usurpations and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the Mighty.</p>
                        <p>When this Nation groaned under those heavy burthens and pressures that were laid upon its shoulder by the last King of <hi>England,</hi> and his subordinate Ministers, it pleased God to raise you up, and to fill you with strength and wisdome, for the weakning of that Arm by which they were imposed, and for the loosing▪ of those galling Cords with which they were bounden. In which work you did valiantly, whiles you were about it: the Lord blessed your Counsels, your Endeavours, and your Armies; for he had heard the cries of the Oppressed, and the sins and cruelties of the Oppressors, and came down, by you, for the work of Deliverance and Judgement. The hearts of your enemies failed them for fear, whiles the hearts of your friends (which were the well-affected and sober of the Land) rejoyced in you, blessed God for you, and rose up before you, and called you blessed. The speeches and passages of your Honourable House, and those memorable Declarations that proceeded from you in the years 1641 and 1642, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the view of the world, (worthy to be written in Letters of Gold, and to be read in every succeeding Generation for your Eternal Fame) were filled with such strains of Wisdom, Righteousness, and true Reason, and carried in them so clear and full a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of your Honourable Intentions to assert and maintain the Legal and Fundamental Liberties, as well Religious as Civil, of the Free-born people of the Land; as that the well-affected to the Interest of the Commonwealth, thought themselves happy in you, and united, as one man, to stand by you unto their utmost hazard.</p>
                        <p>But behold! when <hi>Joshua</hi> (in <hi>Zachary</hi>'s Vision) stood before the Angel of the Lord, <hi>Satan</hi> was observed standing at his right hand. Endeavours were not wanting to stifle the Masculine Spirit of the Nations Freedom, as it lay in the Cradle. Envy, that Infernal Fury, had prepared a viperous Wreath for that purpose, and laid about her abundantly, by means of such men, in whom self-interest had the pre-eminence: so that by the Apostacies, the Lusts, Will and Power of many Members (the portion of whom, we hope, it is not to sit again within your walls, except with hearts repenting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) when the old and open Adversary could not give you the foil, you were, at length, rendred utterly uncapable of raising up that Building to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59153:3"/> its due and expected height, of which you gave assurance by your prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and honourable beginnings. By means whereof, that Cause, at first by you espoused, seemed to be forsaken, and the honest interest of the Nation exposed to the lust and power of men, as much as ever.</p>
                        <p>But the God of Mercies hath not yet (we see) forgotten It nor us, who by a most stupendious and unexpected providence, hath called you together to your old work again, through the mediation of the Army (which is indeed your Army) and other Worthies, who have, at last, we trust, remembred rheir old Engagements, Promises, Vows, Fastings, Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and who are to be remembred by us with all respects of thankfulness and honour for this their interposure: so that the most High hath intrusted you once more with the tender and (hitherto) oppressed Cause of the Commonwealth, and hath determined to try whether you will go on to finish that work to which at first you set your hands. We abundantly rejoyce in your gathering together; and are humbly, yet confidently, perswaded that our good God hath honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with this opportunity, that you, under Him, might glorifie and honour us with a just and well-grounded settlement. Our prayers therefore are for you, and our expectations are exceedingly upon you; and seeing you are thus revived and raised up from that death wherein you were held, let the mighty works of Judgement, Wisdome, Courage, Righteousness, and a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Reformation, shew forth themselves in you. Arise, Honoured Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, and stretch out your arm the second time to save us from confusion, and to secure our Fundamental Liberties. Your very Enemies expect (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though with fear and anguish of soul) that great things will be done by you. The great Affairs of the Commonwealth rest now upon your shoulders; and should you lay it down without such provisions made for it, as the present day doth loudly call for, it will leave an indelible stain of dishonor and reproach upon you to all posterity.</p>
                        <p>We are not altogether insensible of the weight and difficulty of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors present employment: Yet the Lord of Hosts hath, through his wise and mighty disposure of things, in some measure calmed the spirit of the people about you, whose eyes are (yet again) fixt on you for an establishment. We shall therefore presume, in all humility, and with a spirit of Free-born En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishmen, briefly to represent unto this Honourable House our good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the peace and common settlement of the Nation, in these humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations and Proposals, which follow.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>We humbly conceive,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1 That the want of a firm <hi>Basis</hi> for Government in some years past, since the form of the former Government hath seemed to be taken down, hath been the door of occasion and advantage set open for him to enter in and exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that hath had a lust to rule by instruments of a new device. And that the want of such a manifest <hi>Basis</hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ommonwealth, hath given occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, during the sitting of by▪ past Assemblies, to several discontented parties amongst us, to advance their hopes and endeavours for the reviving of their particular Interests which are inconsistent with common freedome, by Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other means less warrantable, promoted by the old Cavalier-party, and the rigid Presbyterian; of which your Petitioners have had frequent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation and experience: and particularly during the sitting of the last As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 That a succeeding Parliament may abrogate and make null (if they
<pb facs="tcp:59153:4"/> please) any Law that is enacted by the <hi>bare</hi> and <hi>single</hi> Authority of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament</p>
                        <p n="3">3 That if the case be such, it is simply necessary, for the cutting off of all advantages o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> usurpation and Domestick disturbance, and for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of peace, that some expedient be found out, and seasonably conclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d on, which may be a <hi>Boundary,</hi> in reason and common judgement, to all future Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>resentatives of the people: which expedient may contain a <hi>Basis</hi> for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment stated and made unalterable.</p>
                        <p>In order whereunto, and with all respect to the Wisdome of this House, we humbly propose and desire,</p>
                        <p n="1">1 <hi>That a</hi> Draught <hi>of an Agreement of the people may be made, and tendred to these Nations for their cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nt and particular subscriptions; of which there were some Ess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ys publish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d and offered to publike view,</hi> Anno 1649. <hi>one of which was presented to this Parliament by the Army; and concerning which work, the Compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rs and Promoters thereof delivered this Judgement, That it was</hi> visibly of highest moment to the Publike; <hi>and that it contained</hi> the best and most hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful foundations of the peace and future well-Government of this Nation, that they <hi>could devise or think on,</hi> within the line of humane power: <hi>and desired</hi> that it might remain upon Record <hi>before You,</hi> a perpetual Witness of their real Intentions and utmost Endeavours for a sound and equal settlement.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 <hi>That this Draught for Settlement, after the manner of an Agreement of the People, may, after the subscriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s of the Parliament and Army, be transmitted to the People, with a Declaration from this Honourable House, designing to convince their judgements of the goodness and worth thereof, and to ingage their affections to acquiesce therein, and to act in Peace and Love according to the tenor and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>of.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3 <hi>That upon the general subscriptions of the said Agreement by the People, or by the well-aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cted amongst th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>m, it may be returned to this Parliament, and there receive such further adventitious Confirmations, as to the wisdome of this Supreme Court shall se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>m most meet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4 <hi>That, for the preventing of such mischiefs and evils which may fall out through the giddiness and dis-affection of the multitude in their Elections of future Parliaments, and through their inclinations to</hi> Monarchy, <hi>and to a</hi> coercive <hi>power in matters of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ligion, It may be provided in the</hi> Agreement <hi>herein meant and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, That upon the election of every succeeding Parliament, a competent number of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n may be chosen also, by Electors, men of such Qualifications as are most pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ad them to the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>king of a good choice; (which Electors may be such only, who are expresly against the old Monarchy, and against all exercise of force, or of the Civil Sword in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>se things which are more especially of God, or over the consciences of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n) And that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>se men thus chos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n, sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l sit, during the Session of Parliament, to observe whether a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y thing be promoted or intended by the Parliament or any particular M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>mber thereof, contrary to such an</hi> Agreement; <hi>and to signifie it to the Commonwealth; and to take such other courses as the exigency of such a thing shall requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5 <hi>Although th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Liberties and Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>domes of the People contain in them the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of</hi> Conscience, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>re the former is perfectly setl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d, the later is also provid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d for; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t, that we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>w o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r tender regard to the Kingly Office of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t, and our app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ehension of the dreadfulness of intrenching upon his Royal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who alone rules ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r the Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cience; we humbly desire, that all such whose Principles and Practices are not offensive to, but consistent with the publike peace,
<pb facs="tcp:59153:4"/> may be tolerated and protected in the profession of their judgements: and that all Laws,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the contrary thereof, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y be vacated and made null.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6 <hi>That your Honours would be pleased to proceed in your wonted wisdome and courage, as to the settlement of the Nation in general, so to the taking away of all grievances in particular, that Justice may be speedily, and without unnec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ry ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and delayes administred, That the Trade of the Nation, now decayed, may be advanced, That Oppression and Vice may be discouraged, and That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>odlin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ss and Vertue may receive all due honour, and That the Mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ia may be s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>tled in the hands of trusty and well-aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d men. In all thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> particulars we prostrate our judgments before this Honourable Parliament.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your Petitioners have faithfully represented themselves to you, and are cheerfully ready to stand by you in your Designs for publike good. We are very confident, that except something remarkable, and of plain ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the purposes aforesaid, be done, you and all the honest people of the Nations, that now close with you, and gratulate your Return, will be more deeply baptized into the black spirit of sham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, dishonor and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, then ever you were like to be before; and the well-affected left, together with your selves, to the lust and pleasure of the next Tyrant, or to the outrage of the numerous and dis-affected multitude, who have not yet had much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aste of the goodness of a Free-State or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Your judgements, after all the expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ience you have had of our many Changes, will dictate to you what is to be done. And we hope and trust, that your Consciences, your Honours, and your own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Interests also, will call upon you for the doing thereof. The Nation expects thorow and plain dealing from you now, above all men. Go on then and prosper in the great work of Reformation, that you may be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>The Patrons of the Commonwealth:</hi> And God, the Great Judge of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, over-awe your hearts, and keep you close to the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to which he hath called you, without turning aside to the right hand, or to the left.</p>
                        <closer>Thus pray your Petitioners.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>THe recital of this Address (which the Author, with many others, under whose notice it came, could not with much peace of conscience s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer to lye dormant, although it be not brought to the Door of Parliament in that manner, wherein it was at first intended) will not, I hope, be made to suffer much under an evil Resentment upon its presentation to the hand of this Council, because it bears a testimony about it of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors good affections to the Parliament, this Army, and the Commonwealth; nor may it be wholly sentenced with imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, in regard the day of settlement is not yet over, and the bounds of liberty not extended so fully as is requisite to such a settlement, as the following Discourse, made by way of inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Address now recited, will demonstrate.</p>
            <p>This Petition (then) the Remonstrative and Epilogizing part
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59153:5"/> thereof being excepted) humbly presents the things which are more especially contained in it, unto serious judgement, under considerations; and Articles of Proposal▪ issuing forth, for the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> part, upon those considerations. I will humbly take leave to inlarge, and reason a little upon both, and do hope to obtain the patience of this Honoured Council in so doing: which hope is better founded, then that which hath no ground; for you your selves have given the greatest part of occasion to this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; as it may be seen throughout. (But to return to our Address.)</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is a vulgar opinion, (how sound or unsound soever) that the antient foundations of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> are out of course, and that it hath no Government but that of the Sword, and such as it shall please from time to time to create and set up. For the Supreme Legislative Power for Ruling, is known to have been invested in the King, the House of Lords, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament: The two former of which Estates being removed, it is (although erroniously) apprehended, that the third falls of it self. Now whiles such an opinion reigns in the judgements of men, and from thence influenceth their affections, it is no hard thing to conjecture how easie they may be provoked to serve the ends of the Old Malignant Spirit, whensoever it shall please to rise. And it is very observeable, that the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the late Insurrection discovered this advantage, as their Declarations make manifest, of which it is vehemently to be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected and feared, they would have made much use, had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign received any prosperous beginning. The people call that peace (such as it was) to mind, which they enjoyed when <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power</hi> was in its glory: They observe further, that since the day there was no King in <hi>England,</hi> the Nation hath been expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to the perillous hazards of divers and fearful changes; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they conclude, that we shall have no lasting peace without a King; and this makes them look backward with a lustful heart after the Old Government again, because they have neither the experience, nor the knowledge of a <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 It was observed how the Spirit of the Prelatical Party was inflamed and ingaged upon endeavours against that Christi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty now in use, and for the reducing of dissenting Christians unto the old <hi>uniformity</hi> in matters of <hi>Faith and Worship;</hi> and that, during the last Assembly under the late <hi>Protector.</hi> Can it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59153:5"/> be imagined that ever they would have raised their hopes up t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that height, and have laboured so earnestly to obtain their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, if they had known they should not have prevailed? and know it they might, in case Parliaments were prohibited from answering such desires. It is to be feared, that whiles Parliaments are at liberty to grant, there will not be Petitioners wanting to ask, for an <hi>Act</hi> or an Ordinance to molest and trouble even peaceable-minded people, because they make not one mind and judgement with others in some particular points of Religion; and peradventure some succeeding Parliament may be solicited with one Petition to chuse a King again out of <hi>the Family of the Stuarts,</hi> when the Royal Spirit shall become willing to act for the obtaining of that by <hi>desire,</hi> which it could not gain by <hi>force.</hi> But if such a <hi>Basis</hi> and <hi>Boundary</hi> were setled, of the want of which the first <hi>consideration</hi> insinuates a complaint, it would put the said turbulent spirit to rebuke, and cause it to surcease its action, and in short time incline such as are led by that spirit, to rest on it, as perceiving now at length what they must trust to, although haply they may not have so good a liking thereof upon its first crection.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The same hand that gathers together, and builds up, may at another time (<hi>eodem jure</hi>) pull down, and scatter abroad: No instances more ordinary then those of this kind: How then will the Honour of this present Parliament, and the just Liberties of the good people of the Land be preserved and maintained in that due respect and state, as become both, if another day may lay the glory of their best and choicest <hi>acts</hi> in the <hi>dust?</hi> The same Parliament may undo that anon, which it self made up but now: So 'tis confest, that a succeeding Parliament may devoure and break in pieces the best compacted frame made by the <hi>simple</hi> and <hi>bare</hi> Authoity of a former, and may stamp the residue under its feet. If then (Gentlemen) you are careful to keep that ground which the Parliament and your selves have gained (and it is monstrous to think otherwise of you;) and to gain that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into the same possession or custody which remains yet unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, (receive this word from the mouth of a worm) Let all heedfulness and diligence possible be used to set <hi>limits</hi> and <hi>bounds</hi> to all future Powers, that they may not break over to invade the peoples <hi>Rights:</hi> And let all hazards be provided against (except that against which there is no provision to be made) I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59153:6"/> mean an irresistable and over-flowing force, out of whose hands no humane power can redeem.) By which one work, the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> in Parliament and Army will more enoble themselves and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitate posterity, then by an hundred Acts or Ordinances made without such a preceding provision. And it is to be hoped, that if such a <hi>settlement</hi> be laid, and <hi>limits</hi> fixed, the powers of Heaven will so far own it, and stand up so close to it, as that the most Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and Malignant Interest in the world shall never be able to subvert and destroy it, nor obscure its glory; but that all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to that purpose shall prove most fatal to the undertakers thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor is it much, that Parliaments sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld have <hi>Boundaries</hi> set to their Power and Authority. The great Creator of the world hath prefixed to all his creatures their proper <hi>limits:</hi> He hath set bounds to the Sea, beyond which it may not pass; and other creatures have their Regions and Elements, as their <hi>bounded Spheres of Action:</hi> Man also is confined, both in his power, and his being. It should not then sound harsh in any ears, that such Supreme Courts, being Bodies Civil, should have their spheres assigned to them. Our Ancestors have been commended for their wisdome and care by some, in limiting and setting out the <hi>being, acting,</hi> and <hi>continuing,</hi> even of <hi>Parliaments</hi> themselves. It is true, we have some assurance that our Representatives in that <hi>High Court</hi> (because they are our Representatives, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen by us) will steer directly to the peoples good, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed those bounds, lest by doing otherwise, their Honors should sustain a loss: But it is a greater assurance, if they may not trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress, but with the peril of their lives, which danger may be still before their eyes, if they also are confined within such a Law which they may not abrogate, but with capital sufferings, as the guilt of such a Treason doth deserve. Thus much only for inlargement upon the considerations offered in the first place.</p>
            <p n="5">5 As for the Articles of Proposal comprehended in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress and Petition before mentioned, the sum and substance of them have been so much, and so earnestly contended for already, that there would be the less to be done here upon them, were the hearts and souls of all parties inclined to follow their own principles with such exactness as becomes men of reason, worth, and honour; but because the contrary is incident to our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59153:6"/> state, of which we have had too much experience, it wil not, I hope, be grievous to insist a little on some of those parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>The Original of all just Power and Authority is resolved into the peoples hands, and that by the judgement of the Parliament it self. The Statesmen tell us of three wayes, by which Ruling Powers are set up for Government. The first is by <hi>Divine Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration,</hi> or immediate Dictate of God: By this way <hi>Moses,</hi> that meek spirit, became a Governour over the Tribes of <hi>Israel.</hi> The second is by <hi>Conquest;</hi> and the last is by popular <hi>consent.</hi> There is no manifest claim laid by our Rulers to either of the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and if there were, it is a work of no insuperable difficulty to implead and invalidate the Title. The last way then is that in which we are to settle, and according to the rational rules whereof, the course of Government is to be steered. The Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this present Parliament were chosen by the people; it must be confessed; and thereupon we have assurance, that they will dispose things so, that the well-affected and more judicious sort may rejoyce in them, and bless the Lord that ever they were chosen: which disposure of things must be by setling the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in such a way, that their own and the Nations just Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties (which are now the price of much blood and treasure) may be preserved from the uncertain determinations of future Ruling men, as far as humane wisdome can secure them. The Commonwealth labours under a double Epidemical distemper; there is a restless spirit of faction and animosity carrying men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side towards private interests; and there is a spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, in respect of publike <hi>Administrations,</hi> no party being well and throughly perswaded, where, in the midst of those great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions, which their eyes have seen, they shall at last come to bottom. (As for any forraign danger threatning us, it receives life from these, and will vanish, as the people are recovered out of this complex disease:) What is more likely to effect the cure hereof, (I speak with submission) then for our Noble Patriots in Parliament and Army, to endeavour their utmost for the drawing of the people into a <hi>general Consent and Agreement?</hi> which is to be done not by force and violence, or by any interminating Law, but by an honourable example, and by real demonstrations, and solid reasons, leading the judgements and the consciences of the yet-unperswaded willingly captive thereunto, according to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59153:7"/> sense and true intention of the second Article. What can be more likely to correct and carry away those peccant humours in the disaffected sort, and to extinguish those animosities which kindle and rise up between party and party, then to present them with one <hi>common Basis and Foundation,</hi> on which every ones Common Right may be secured? And when the more discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed party shall have some sight of that preservative, and of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign good which lieth therein, and shall perceive withall, that a restraint is laid upon their spirit of violence, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not invade the common liberty and right of their neighbours at their pleasure, they will, ere long, rest themselves contented, and sit down under the Government in peace, when they see their own liberties and properties secured by it.</p>
            <p n="6">6 A supposition, that a very considerable part of the people will not consent to, and subscribe such Articles as such an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment should contain, will not I hope supersede the motion, nor disingage those whom it may more especially concern, from endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to promote it: For, let it be granted that such a number, who having their judgements captivated by their passions, are thereby rendred uncapable of seeing the way to publike good, will thereupon refuse to yield their consents to the laying of this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation-stone; shall this hinder those who are better disposed, and less prejudiced, to act towards such a settlement, which hath been so solemnly declared and adjudged to be <hi>visibly of highest moment to the Publike?</hi> An Act of Parliament is interpretatively, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mode of Parliament, an Act of the whole House, although of four hundred Members, one hundred ninety and nine be negative in passing the Bill; and such an Act, if it be general, concludes and shuts up every particular Member of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth unto obedience, although those Gentlemen chosen for Knights and Burgesses had not the voice of every particular and individual person therein. If the major part consent and subscribe to such an <hi>Agreement,</hi> why may it not be taken for the agreement of the whole? Or, should the number of the non-subscribers weigh down the balance, and upon the account, come forth the greater; shall I say it is then question, whether the well-affected to that way should neglect the means of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, and of the securing of their own Rights and Liberties to themselves and their posterities, because their number is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded? But if it be provided that the Non-Subscribers shall be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59153:7"/> uncapable of any Publike Trust or place of profit in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and of giving their voices for Members to sit and act in the Supreme Court; and if those also were substracted from the number of the whole Body, who are indeed the conquered Party in the Nation; if also some active men, men that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the nature and end of this work, and are able to answer the objections, and to remove the scruples which haply may be (mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destly) made against it, or raised up concerning it; (although such a draught should be made most plain, and as little liable to excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as possible) I say, if such men were imployed in every County for the management of the business, in tendering such a draught to the people, and in taking their subscriptions, methinks a very competent, yea, a very considerable measure of confidence may be adventured, that the Subscribers would upon these terms amount to far the greater number of the people.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Had such a draught, upon which the eye of this present dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is fastned, been concluded on, compleated with subscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as aforesaid, and made unalterable by any Representative Power whatsoever, and had it been made High-Treason by the same <hi>Agreement</hi> for any person whatsoever to endeavour the subversion or alteration thereof by force or counsel, it is more then probable, that those attempts that have been of late made against the present Power, and for the re-inforcing of another, would never have been conceived, or brought forth, because of the pre-ingagement of the spirit of the people in the said Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or, if those men in whom the spirit of discontent and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy is in its elevation, should have aduentured, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, actually to endeavour the promotion of their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular interests, in direct opposition to the general <hi>settlement,</hi> a Tryal of such men, as Traytors to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> at an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Assize, in the face of the County, where such a fact should be found to have been committed, (in which Tryal, those Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws contained in the <hi>Agreement,</hi> against which the malefactors have risen up, together with the plainness of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of those Laws to publike good, should be explained to the people, and inculcated upon their minds, and the desperateness and cursedness of the attempt for their subversion unravelled and set forth, to the utter detestation of the hearers) I say, that an open Tryal of two or three of the principal, or Ring-leaders of such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> manner and the execution of them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59153:8"/> would strike the heart of Cavalierism with more fear, dread and horror, and would be more likely to wear out their spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then the securing of an hundred of them in a time of suspiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and danger, and committing of them to the custody of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal, till the cloud be a little overblown; this later being sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them as an honour, not as a disparagement, to their Cause.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And for the prevention of such differences as may possibly, arise between those persons, which should be called together out of every pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of the well-affected sort, for the stating and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling of such Laws and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticles as that Agreement must con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ist of, were that Compilement now to be made without a Patern, That Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught which was once prepared and offered to this Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, by the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Council of War (of which our Address makes mention) may, it having received (if there be need thereof) such alterations or emendations as are found need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, by consulting with the Natural and National Rights of the People, and with some other Draughts of the same kinde, be that Body in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o which both Parliament and Army may first inspire life, by gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing their consent and subscribing it, and by commending it therewith to us in the Countries round about them, as a <hi>Testimony of their real intentions and utmost endeavours for a sound and equal settlement.</hi> Then shall they be called the <hi>Repairers of the Breach, and the Restorers of paths to dwell in:</hi> and until then, that <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> of which there is so much talk in the World, will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the subtilty of the Foxes, and the raging fury of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Forrest.</p>
            <p n="9">9. There is a double evil to be endeavoured to be excluded by them that sit at the Helm, an <hi>absolute Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>persecution for Conscience:</hi> the establishing of a <hi>Free Commonwealth,</hi> and the securing of it from the force and violence of these two evil spirits, is an eminent attainment: <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus est.</hi> A numerous multitude remember the old Government by Kings; and that <hi>Ʋniformity</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> which was contended for by a Law, when <hi>Episcopacy</hi> was in its strength; and they retain a good liking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with a reflection of disdain and hatred upon those, as the cause of all their troubles, that have had a hand in the demolishing of these, and now take pleasure in their Ruines. This interest (it may be said) will have the major voice in the Election of <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgesses</hi> for Parliament; and such men are likely to be sent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59153:8"/> thither, by their choice, who are led by the same spirit with them: Is not the <hi>New Commonwealth</hi> in danger now? Parliaments also are errable, and may be swayed to gratifie particular interests too much, against the <hi>Common Right of all:</hi> And being now supposed to be made up of such, for the most part, who bear upon them the Image of the Electors, will they not introduce <hi>Monarchy</hi> again, and uncharm and set at liberty that restless <hi>spirit of persecution,</hi> which finds the <hi>Rooms</hi> of too many professing men <hi>swept and garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed</hi> for its entertainment? what? shall we think that that Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Supreme <hi>Court,</hi> which ought (as the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> well saith) <hi>To give example unto all inferiour Courts,</hi> will move or act directly and manifestly contrary to that, whereunto they have consented, and manifested their <hi>consent by subscription</hi> lying upon publique and perpetual Record, and by consenting have, as far as in them lieth, made unchangable? shall we think that such a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will endeavour to destroy and lay wast such a <hi>Foundation,</hi> which not only themselves, but those also by whom they are more manifestly intrusted, conspired together to make unmovable, and to render it the sure <hi>Basis</hi> or <hi>Bottom</hi> for Government? Is all Faith and Humane stedfastness exiled the Breasts and Consciences of English men professing Christianity; and gone to attend in service upon the Courts of <hi>Pagans?</hi> No: It is to be presumed, that a few years will extinguish those discontents and heart-burnings which are in men, in as many, at least, as need to be feared in this work: And that when they shall behold real intentions and proportionable endeavours for publick good and settlement, they will content themselves to build uniformly on that Foundation, which they shall find laid for such a purpose. But if doubts do still remain, notwithstanding this, ▪concerning the inclinations of succeeding Parliaments to that <hi>ground and settlement,</hi> Let additional cautions and provisions be made, and included in that <hi>Agreement,</hi> for the further security thereof; Let it be declared and agreed that every Member of Parliament shall take a <hi>Solemn Oath</hi> (a most Religious Bond) not to endeavour the Abrogation or Alteration of this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the People;</hi> and let it be put in execution according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and besides, it may be provided in the same, That some one man be chosen at every Parliament-election, out of every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to make an Assembly, during the sitting of Parliament, whose chief trust may be, to see that nothing be done contrary to that <hi>Fundamental Law;</hi> And let this choice be to be made by such on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59153:9"/> as are manifestly known to be against the ejected <hi>Monarchy, and for the liberty of Conscience:</hi> And if, after all these preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive cautions, there be yet doubt and cause for doubting, the Law of necessity remains to be put in ure, which is to be the last refuge for safety, when all means else do fail; and (I speak under favour all along) there is an Army that is needful to be kept up, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> thus setled, from rending winds and storms, whiles it is tender and young.</p>
            <p n="10">10. A motion to the creating of such an Assembly forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, which is to oversee the peoples Liberties contained in that great <hi>Charter,</hi> and to preserve them from violence and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, must not prove irksome or displeasing to the severer sort of <hi>Commonwealths-men.</hi> These Patriots are either, such as stand averse to that Liberty of Conscience spoken of before, or such whose judgements and affections have adopted it, and are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for it. The men of the first sort, I hope, will not obtain that happiness (or rather unhappiness) as to be heard and answered in their Designs and Desires; God (I trust) hath provided some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing for the present Generation of his people, after all these Turns and Tumults, then to give up dissenting Christians into the wills and hands of such men: And if these drive forward to the setling of an <hi>absolute Commonwealth,</hi> without some such cautions and provisions as are intended in the former Section; it is to be feared that the <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> will at length be undermined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the <hi>Abetters</hi> thereof rooted out; there being nothing more probable then that the well-affected to <hi>Religious Freedom</hi> will be out-voiced in chusing Members for our great Court of Parliament (especially as the case yet stands with the people:) what manner of men then, that great Council will consist of, and which way they will set their faces, is no hard matter to divine: so that those who are for the laying of the foundation of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth without a Fundamental <hi>Agreement of the People;</hi> without swearing, &amp; thereby most solemnly obliging, all Parliament Men to give all true and faithful respect and observation to that <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> without a number of men to sit &amp; observe, that the Laws and Articles of the <hi>Agreement</hi> be kept inviolable, even by Parliaments themselves; and without an Army (at least, for the present, as the state of things yet is) to suppress all Insurrections that intend the general Disturbance of the Peace of the Commonwealth; or without some other means equivalent, or Superiour in strength,
<pb facs="tcp:59153:9"/> to these for common security (for I dare not to prescribe with peremptoriness) I say, Those men who are driving on in publick Affairs without this, may be suspected for such, who (either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly or of set purpose) contend to have one door yet kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen for Tyranny and oppression to enter in upon its next Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. But the Parliament and Army have given some reason to assure us, that there is an heart of loyalty to that <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> at first contended for, lodged in their Bosoms: Let not then the formalities and punctilioes of a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> become the subject of contention, to the loss of the substance and life of the whole interest. If the Nation be to be preserved from the return of that Monarchy, under whose Power and Tyranny it once groaned, and from that bloudy arm of persecution for Conscience in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious things which hath been lifted up too often to the ruine of many precious men; and if the Parliament and their Army, would be the saviours thereof from these in this day of its Distress and Difficulty, let it not be thought much by any of them, that such means as is necessary, should be imployed for the effecting of such a Salvation and Protection; although those means, so to be imployed or set up, comport not so exactly with the absoluteness of a <hi>Commonwealth-form.</hi> But by this that hath been proposed as a means for security, there is nothing added, except that which first passeth through the consent and approbation of the people, in whom the Authority of erecting Governments resides, (as it hath been said) and so consequently, nothing but what may pass without much ado with all those whose hearts and souls are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and devoted to the general peace, just liberty, and perfect settlement of the people.</p>
            <p n="11">11 The sixth Article in the Petition pre-inserted, is wholly bestowed and laid out upon, and in the behalf of that great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, which is opposed with so much fiery zeal by some, and so curtailed and strait-laced by others; I mean, <hi>Liberty of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> in points of Faith, and of Divine Worship. When the Rights and Freedomes of the people are fully, clearly, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly stated and secured, in such a way, and upon such terms as have been shewed in the former periods, there is no need that any more should be done for this particular <hi>Liberty:</hi> Every man may sit down under his own Vine, and may (<hi>salvâ conscientia sua</hi>) possess his soul in patience and quietness; the heavy fingers of the more tyrannizing sort being, by that settlement, removed
<pb facs="tcp:59153:10"/> and prohibited from falling on that tender part. Yet in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> times and before such an Agreement and Government is setled, it is humbly desired in this Article, <hi>That those whose principles and practises are not offensive to the publike peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, may be tolerated and protected in the profession of their Faith and Judgement,</hi> however dissenting from the commonly-recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved principles in Religion) and for that purpose, <hi>that all Laws,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the contrary thereof, may be vacated and made null.</hi> This Article Petitions for no more, then what hath been <hi>solemnly and deliberately</hi> declared and published by the Council of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> (when time was) in their draught of the <hi>Agreement</hi> before quoted, as their judgement and desire: And of which, as being a part of that model framed and drawn up by <hi>them,</hi> they professed, that according to the utmost extent of their judgements, <hi>it was the way to a most just and equal settlement.</hi> According to which also, that <hi>Instrument of Government,</hi> seemingly intended for the <hi>Magna Charta of the Commonwealth;</hi> and to rule after the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles therein, that <hi>Protector,</hi> who received his very <hi>Being</hi> of <hi>Protector</hi> at the same instant with it, lifted up his <hi>hand,</hi> and swore by <hi>Him that liveth for ever and ever</hi> (the fulfilling of which oath, even in this very point of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and the Catastrophe of that Family, is to be observed: <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>The passages of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Great Man, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his entrance into that Government, might be recorded with very material observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be also made thereon, but that I list not to indulge or act in▪ their humour, who cryed</hi> Hosanna t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Him, <hi>whiles he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but after death do crucifie him; which is a most ridiculous and unbeseeming temper, and the constant character of the vulgar spirit▪ Read</hi> Conscience Oppression <hi>set out in his time.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>That In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of Government,</hi> I say, declared and setled this liberty, to the content and pleasure of the dissenting godly in the Land, in as full and as large a way (upon the matter) as this Article desires; so that our lips move not herein for any new Thing.</p>
            <p n="12">12 The common sort, whose understandings are not so well acquainted with the work of the Gospel, nor so considerate of the manner of its setling truth upon the hearts and consciences of men, as is to be desired, are apt and ready, at every turn, to charge the commotions and broils rising up in the Land, upon the head of the Sectaries, men dissenting from them in matters of Faith and Worship; concluding and crying out amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to the inraging one of another, that we shall never have
<pb facs="tcp:59153:10"/> any l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sting peace whiles so many different Professions (Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they say) are tolerated by Authority. So that if ever there be an opportunity offered to them, and they therein get the head, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail (but) a little, this erronious perswasion of theirs will arm them with rage, and animate their fury against very many peaceable and well-affected people in the Nations, even to the making of them a prey to the outragious lust and power of these sons of violence. It is therefore most seriously to be wished, and as carefully to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured, that there be a proceeding to the settlement of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without any Magistratical Cognizance of Dissenters about Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things; and that the peace of the Commonwealth may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served upon that settlement; that that sort of men, in whom the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid mistake and false imagination domineers, may learn the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vanity of such their conception, and repent thereof, when they shall see peace and prosperity within our walls, standing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a <hi>Toleration</hi> of dissenting Christians.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but declare my wonder (and the wonder of many more also) at that spirit of this Council, manifested in the sixth Proposal of your Humble Petition and Address to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in these words: <hi>That all persons that profess Faith in God the Father, and in Jesus Christ, his Eternal Son, the true God; and in the Holy Spirit, God coequal with the Father and the Son, one God blessed for ever; and do acknowledge the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Testament to be the revealed or written Word or Will of God, shall not be restrained from their profession, but have due incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and equal protection in the profession of their Faith, and exercise of Religion: Provided that they abuse not, &amp;c.</hi> Who would have imagined that ever such a thing as this is, should issue forth from between the feet of such a Generation? I will humbly take the boldness, as a Spectator only of these transactions, to reason and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate a little with that spirit, wherewith you were acted in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling and drawing up of this Proposal: and this I will do, out of that respect I bear and owe to the Regal Dignity of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus; and that obligation which lieth upon me (a servant of the same Jesus) to vindicate his Crown out of the hands of all unjust usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation whatsoever: yet with the salvage of all respects of honour and esteem due to you (magnanimous and victorious <hi>Heroes</hi>) the Promoters of the said Petition; because I have yet this full perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concerning you, that if you knew that the said sixth Proposal, or any part or member thereof, did look with any (the least) maligne aspect upon the Kingdome of Christ, you would take far more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59153:11"/> pains to expunge and blot it out from before the eyes of <hi>Parliament;</hi> then, I suppose, you took to draw it up, and to present it to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is (then) very questionable, whether that spirit, by which this proposal concerning <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> was projected and framed, were of God, and not rather a spirit of <hi>selfishness</hi> and <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality,</hi> whose way of acting is beneath, and most commonly against that of the Gospel: For, besides what is done to the discovery of its Descent and Lineage, by the intent and scope of the said Proposal, which it may and must be interpreted to design and make towards, the very structure and frame thereof is significant enough, that the Artificers were not therein <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>taught of God;</hi> and that the work it self was not carried up by a Divine <hi>Hand.</hi> First, you draw up, and give in such a Symbol and <hi>Confession</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> or things to be believed, as necessary to <hi>obtain the protection of the State,</hi> as is not by the Holy Spirit made necessary to the enjoyment or <hi>possession of Heaven.</hi> Jesus Christ in that most sweet and Divine Confession and Supplication of his to his Father, <hi>John 17. ver.</hi> 3. saith thus: <hi>This is life eternal, to know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent; i. e.</hi> Those who know and acknowledge with heart and conscience, the Father for their only true God, or most Soveraign Lord; and who in like manner acknowledge Jesus Christ for the Messiah, or Sent of God, are the undoubted Sons and Heirs of Eternal Life. And <hi>Paul,</hi> that eminent and able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the <hi>New Testament,</hi> describes the word of Faith thus in <hi>Rom. 10. That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe with thy heart that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the gate that opens into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is yet to come, is, by the great Oracle of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, declared to be <hi>strait;</hi> and it is no part of the prudence of man (nor doth it savour of true wisdome in him, to do as you have done,) neither is it a thing pertinent to man, for whose sake this door or in let into Life is set open, to make it straiter then the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Life hath made it. Or shall we think it will redound to the honour or advantage of any Commonwealth or Kingdome in the world, to make the terms and conditions of obtaining a place of rest and peace in it, more rigid and severe, then those the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Law-giver</hi> hath made for the enjoyment of a <hi>better peace and rest above?</hi> I am reasoning with men of wisdome, and therefore shall forbear many words. It is the judgement of the most judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, sober, and learned sort of Christians almost of all parties now, <hi>That the Fundamentals of Faith</hi> (I mean, such things as are simply
<pb facs="tcp:59153:11"/> necessary to be believed, in order to the enjoyment of life everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>are few and clear;</hi> and therein they conclude with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> but condemn <hi>Athanasius</hi> for drawing out his Creed into such a tedious Bed-roll of particulars, and therein fentencing all who dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in any one point with an <hi>Anathema Maranatha.</hi> Secondly, there is not that care and exactness used by you, as is requisite to a work of this moment, in speaking concerning the Holy Scriptures; when you make the acknowledgement of the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Testament for the revealed or written Word or Will of God, as another member of your Creed, necessary to be believed, in order to mens receiving encouragement and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For this saying, <hi>That the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, are the revealed or written Word or Will of God,</hi> can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no tolerable construction in reason, and as the thing will bear, otherwise then what the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> saith of the Scripture, that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, divinely inspired; or that the men which, time after time, were imployed in writing them, were set to work, and enlightned and directed in their work by the Holy Chost: And in this sense indeed, they may be said to be the Will of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> such a work as was dispatcht and commended to the world by the Will and direction of God: But otherwise for the subject matter of Scripture, or things written, a very considerable par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof is hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storical, and relates (although not with such fallibility as other Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories do) the words and facts of men, which were many times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Word or Will of God: As for the Doctrinal, preceptive and promissory part of these sacred leafs, they are in a more neer and tolerable sense, to be called the Word and Will of God. So that this Article of this <hi>Symbolum Armatorum,</hi> or Creed of a Religious and Renowned Army, may prove a gin, and a snare, and a rock of offence to some who think as you think, upon the matter; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they cannot speak so as you speak, without some distinction and interpretation, shall have their protection called into question. Thirdly, the compilement of this Proposal, after the manner as you have laid it down, gives occasion unto men not interessed in the work, to conceive and conclude; either first, that the Doctrine of Co-equality of persons in the God-head is not contained in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: Or secondly, that it is not so clearly contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but that it stands in need of some distinct and accurate exposure, else more ordinary capacities could not be able to raise themselves up to the observation and understanding thereof. Or, thirdly, that the Council of Officers stands in direct opposition (in respect of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb facs="tcp:59153:12"/> fellowship) to a particular sort of men that never did them any harm. For after you had spoken your minds concerning the God-head, and the distinction of persons therein, you make the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Divine Authority of the Scriptures another part of those qualifications (<hi>distinctim &amp; separatim</hi>) wherewith those are to be adorned that must expect safety from the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:</hi> As if a man might acknowledge the Scriptures to be true, and of God, and yet deny the Doctrine of the Trinity in the way that it is here propounded. What? would you have us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Doctrine of Co-equality of Persons in the God-head, is not contained in the Scriptures? or else what mean you by this? It is true indeed, the Papists do acknowledge upon occasion, that the Doctrine of the Trinity of Persons in the same substance, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Tradition (in the modern sense of the term Tradition:) And will you make the belief of Traditions necessary, for men to have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of converse in your Commonwealth? It is confessed again by those that are neither <hi>Papists,</hi> nor <hi>Socinians,</hi> that that Doctrine of the Trinity, as proposed by you, is not so clear in Scripture, as some other things of greatest importance: Ah! Gentlemen; will you press so hard upon those whose eyes see not things that are in the dark, that they shall have neither part nor lot in that peace and safety of this Commonwealth, which hath been purchased by your hand, in a great measure thereof; because they do not see that which the most <hi>seeing</hi> part of your selves declare to be mysterious and obscure, and (in a sense) invisible? Or are the <hi>Socinians</hi> men of so ill deservings in your eye, that (although <hi>Paul</hi> nor Jesus exclude them not heaven, by their Creed (as hath been shewn, yet) you will leave them out of your Petition, to stand or fall before the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Commonwealth; and thereby render them obnoxious to the wild Beasts of prey which range abroad in the Dark? what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil have these done against the peace and <hi>Settlement</hi> of the Nation, that they should be the men singled out above all others, and set up as a mark for their Neighbours to shoot their Arrows, sharpened with indignation, against? you cannot, therefore, Oh you mighty Ones! but perceive, how that in the very framing of this Proposal, you were led by a spirit not of God, nor by your own; for then your work would have been more compact, clear, uniform and publickly beneficial; but by a spirit cloathed in <hi>Black,</hi> darkness being the Region thereof; from whence proceeds nothing but disorder, blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed and outrage: you have stumbled in the very draught thereof, and thereby have laid open your weakness: And such indeed hath
<pb facs="tcp:59153:12"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which Divine providence hath thought meet to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spense, of late times especially, to those who have attempted to set up an Image of Doctrine to which they are resolved to force their Brethren to bow down: men never act in a way more unseemly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discreet, and unlike to <hi>men,</hi> then when they endeavour towards the lifting up of Instruments of force to have to do in things pertaining to God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The substance and scope of this Proposal of yours which we now have under question, is to shew what manner of persons they are, and must be, who, you would, should be received into the favour and <hi>protection of the State:</hi> wherein there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation also implicitely and constructively delivered and given, <hi>of that sort of men,</hi> which you are willing should be left out without the Lines of that Protection. Had you left none without that pale, but such whom your <hi>Quondam-General,</hi> and the Nations Protector was willing to have to fall under the cognizance of the <hi>Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate,</hi> in his Speech to the <hi>Parliament, Jan. 22. 1654. pag.</hi> 18, 19. there is not a pen, I dare believe, would have been lifted up to encounter your proceedings herein, except by those who have a mind to lord over the consciences of all men differing from them but in the least points: But that you should leave out a Generation of men, which in the judgement of their Adversaries are contemptible neither for number, nor for their intellectual nor moral Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and these too, many of them instrumental for the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that <hi>Liberty</hi> of which the religious and well-affected amongst the people are partakers, at present; and measure them for destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, rather then preservation, or <hi>protection;</hi> this sheweth you to the world, upon that side which you were not wont to be seen on; for hereby you exhibit your selves to publike view, as men of a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and low spirit, forgetful of your antient principles, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true bounds of Christian Liberty; and not men of publike spirits, as you have formerly shewn your selves to be.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Lord of Hosts made you instrumental and serviceable to the vanquishing of that persecuting power setled in the <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> and to the suppressing of the same power in its forwardness of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to rise up in the High-Presbytery. Can it enter into your thoughts, that the Arm of the <hi>Jehovah</hi> was made yours, and did erect it self in you, to the extorting of that Sword of Persecution <hi>for Conscience</hi> out of the hands of those two interests successively, with an intent that you should at last put it into that hand which may prove most heavy? When the power of prosecuting, and cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:59153:13"/> down men for their Opinions in points of Faith, resided in the Hierarchy or Prelacy, if any rigid censures or determinations pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in their Courts against any, and they were delivered up to be tormented, the <hi>Civil Magistrate</hi> might possibly have been implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have shewn mercy, and to have interposed, by some means or other, for the mitigation (if not the whole taking off) of the judgement threatned: but when those that should be for Cities of Refuge to the oppressed and afflicted, shall themselves be vested with a power to afflict in the same kind; how sad and lamentable is it like to be, when they shall have a mind and will to act according to that power, there being no considerable or equi-ponderating in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest left, as likely to mediate with any spirit of lenity?</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is not long since the spirit of a deep slumber possessed many of you; at which time you appeared to the well-disposed and best<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeing amongst the people, as men that had utterly forgotten your old Ingagements, and the many <hi>Protestations</hi> you made to assert and maintain, to your utmost, the <hi>just Liberties</hi> of the honest people of the Land: Now through the providence of God, you have been awakened to see your own defections, and to re-mind that from whence you were fallen; consider then what agreement and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion there is between your aforesaid Ingagements, and this new Proposal: Shall the glory of your Repentance be stained with acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a more unworthy and unhandsome character, then those of yours were before your <hi>Back-sliding?</hi> You profess that you have attained to a sensibility of your <hi>Apostate state;</hi> be humbly and seriously admonished then to <hi>bring forth fruits meet for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> that God and man may take pleasure in your Revival.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Many of those who dissent from you in Doctrines of God, who are yet peaceable in the Land, were taught by you to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge and desire their liberty in matters of Faith, and their exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the cognizance of any <hi>Civil Judicature</hi> upon their <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</hi> Such a thing as this, your <hi>Declarations,</hi> your <hi>Remonstrances, &amp;c.</hi> contended for, and that too, with so much strength and preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of Evidence, and light of Reason, that some of those whom you now leave to themselves to petition for their own <hi>liberty,</hi> as you have done for yours, became <hi>Proselytes</hi> to you, and to that Cause, at first contended for by you; (to the setling and securing of which, you did most solemnly and seriously ingage your selves) by means of your Declarations, and those other wayes of your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing of it out. Some by-stander unprejudiced, and interessed neither in your wayes, nor in the way of those whom you now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59153:13"/> leave out, may hereupon not unaptly apply those words of the <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist, (Psal.</hi> 119. which were by him intended for a confession of Gods goodness, and of the rich sufficiency of his Laws for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selling) to <hi>the men of your Excommunication,</hi> and say, <hi>they are become wiser then their Teachers, &amp;c.</hi> You were men eminent for publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of spirit; how is your wine turned into water? and you had many sons of imitation, children who drew their lines by your lines, and builded after that plat-form drawn out by your selves: How narrow spirited should these become, if they should take you for their example in this business also; and do as you have done at last?</p>
            <p n="6">6 But you are at variance with your selves in this and some for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Proposals, and tenders of your minds about this kind of <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty;</hi> which is not a matter of much difficulty to make appear. I shall presume upon your patience, whiles I am endeavouring a brief discovery thereof: And although many of your papers will manifest how foully you have fallen upon your selves in this your late at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and expedition; yet (because I would not be over-tedious) I will single out only two for that purpose; <hi>viz.</hi> your <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>August</hi> 2. 1647. and your Draught of an <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> presented to the Parliament; together with a Petition, <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1649. (By the way, I make choice of these two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned works of yours, above any other, out of which to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce instances shewing your <hi>variation,</hi> because these were drawn up by you, and offered at the feet of State, at such times in which there were the greatest, and (seemingly) the most intent endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the laying <hi>foundations</hi> to a <hi>firm and well-grounded peace;</hi> and the times wherein both of these papers were conceived and produced respectively, were such, in which the eyes of men were fixed upon the Army, in expectation of some <hi>great thing;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to be supposed that they did their utmost, according as both seasons required, for the setling and establishing of the Rights and just Liberties of the people, which they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d so frequently and earnestly declared and ingaged to endeavour.) In the former of the said papers, <hi>page</hi> 9. it is propounded, in order to the clearing and securing the Rights and Liberties of the Kingdome, and the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a just and lasting peace, (as the Title of the said Proposals speak) <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>That an Act he passed to take away all Coercive Power, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Jurisdiction of Bishops, and all other Ecclesiastical Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whatsoever, extending to any civil penalties upon any; And to repeal all Laws whereby the Civil Magistracy hath been, or is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59153:14"/> bound, upon any Ecclesiastical censure, to proceed</hi> (ex officio) <hi>unto any civil penalties against any persons so censured: And that there be a repeal of all Acts, or Clauses in any Act, imposing any penalty for not coming to Church, or for meetings elsewhere, for prayer, or other Religious Duties, Exercises or Ordinances; and some other provision to be made for discovering of Papists and popish Recusants, and for disabling of them, and of all Jesuites or Priests, from disturbing the State.</hi>
               </q> Upon which Proposals it may be observed, amongst other things; First, That it was the desire of the Army, that no coercive power about or concerning matters of Religion (that being a part of what before fell under the cognizance of the Ecclesiastical Officers) should continue or reside in the hands of any; for they propose, That all such Jurisdiction of Bishops should be taken away, and this without the least provision or intimation given for the use or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise thereof, by any other Interest whatsoever. Secondly, They leave it to the care of the Parliament to provide onely against the disturbance of the State by Papists or Jesuites, when such Acts which impose any penalties for not coming to Church or for metings else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where for Prayers, or other Religious Duties, Exercises or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, should be by Them repealed. Now if the Exercise of <hi>coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive power, Jurisdiction, or Authority extending to civil penalties for matters Ecclesiastical,</hi> were adjudged unwarrantable, and against the <hi>Rights and Liberties of the People,</hi> and <hi>Peace of the Nation,</hi> when it remained in the hands of the <hi>Bishops,</hi> may it not be supposed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to be of the same evil Nature, and to have the like ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in what hand soever it be? or was it not intended in those dayes to be taken out of their Hands, with a Desire that it should never come into any other? This without controversie, was the Designe of the spirit of the Army at that time; if it can but be called into Remembrance; and thus much also the Proposals themselves, being carefully observed, do, with clearness enough, intimate. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, In your Draught of an Agreement of the People, you in the eighth Head of the said Draught, speaking of the Power and Supreme Trust which the Representatives of the People should be understood to have, <hi>declare and agree</hi> to have it extend (amongst other things) <hi>to the highest and final Judgement concerning all natural or civil things; but not concerning things spiritual or Evangelical.</hi> And concerning Toleration; and the Qualifications of persons to be tolerated by the State, you declare and agree in the third particular under the ninth Article, which is expresly intended for Religion, <q rend="margQuotes">That such as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess faith in God, through Jesus Christ, (however differing in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59153:14"/> from the Doctrine, Worship, or Discipline publickly held forth) shall not be restrained from, but shall be protected in, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of their faith and exercise of religion according to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, in any place (except such as shall be set apart for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship, where we provide not for them, except they have leave) so as they abuse not this Liberty to the Civil Injury of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or to the actual Disturbance of the publick Peace upon their parts.—</q> Now (Gentlemen) let these Passages of yours, fore-recited, be revised by you, and compared with that Proposal, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion and Toleration, which you have now made to this Parliament, and which is now under Debate; and you cannot but observe a very great <hi>Alteration</hi> (I may say, without impeachment of falsehood, or waste made upon your Names or Honours, a very great and most <hi>deplorable Declination</hi>) of Minde and Spirit, about the <hi>Liberty of Religious People,</hi> and that too, in things of greatest mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and importance, being such as respect God, and the Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men. <hi>Produce your strong Reasons;</hi> let the Grounds and Causes of this prodigious Change of yours be manifested, and let it be known, why you are not of the same minde in the things of this concernment, and in order to the setling and securing of the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the people, 1659. as you were of, <hi>August</hi> 1. 1647. and <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. 1649. that so those who made one and the same minde with you, concerning <hi>Liberty</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> may, if your change be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and for the best, convert, with you, to a better, and more so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Judgement (pardon my plainness; for I have it in my heart to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you more, then any <hi>Flatterer</hi> in the world will do, although I thus speak.)</p>
            <p n="7">7. Nor will it be much available to redeem you from under the sufferings of this contradiction, to say, That although you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed petitioned for men of such a Character as you have given in your Proposal, and onely for such, yet you have not petitioned against any other; and so have not offered an occasion to any, to complain of wrong done to them by that Proposal. It is true indeed; some kinde of thanks may (haply) be due to him who will not wish me any harm, although he utterly refuse to wish me well; and in this respect, some tribute of thankfulness may be paid to you, by those for whose Liberty you have propounded nothing; yet it is such that will not much convert to your honour or glory. But secondly, and according to this construction of your Proposal, you leave the men excepted by you, to the mercy of Parliaments; many of whose Members you cannot but know, are, and are likely to be, men of a far
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59153:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59153:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59153:16"/> less Latitude, in regard of Christian Liberty, then your selves: so that your design and undertaking is of a sad regret, even to your selves; for all the water wherewith <hi>Pilate</hi> washed his hands, at the arraignment of Jesus Christ, will never clear him for a man of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, about the death of that Just Person; because he engaged not his utmost to deliver Him from the rage of his cruel and tyrannizing Adversaries. He that redeems not his Neighbour from injury, if it be in the power of his hand to do it, contracts the same guilt upon his soul with him that doth the wrong. Thirdly, and that also which is of an observation no whit inferiour to the other, in your former Proposals, Declarations and publick Tenders, you have asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it for your Judgement, That the way to the settling of the peace of the Nation, and the securing of the Rights and Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erties thereof, is, amongst other things, by providing for the safety of all Christians, however differing in Doctrine, Worship or Discipline, from the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick profession of the Nation. But fourthly and lastly, You have most solemnly engaged your selves, once and again, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God, and in the view and observation of the world, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour your uttermost, for the asserting and vindicating of the just Freedoms of the People; more especially of the well-affected sort: so that it lyeth on you to prove that the men for whom you have spoken neither word nor syllable in your Petition, are disaffected and malignantly enclined, with whose Toleration the peace of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot consist, because of their turbulent and seditious spirit, or that their Liberty of thinking and speaking concerning God, Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the Dictates of their consciences, is unjust, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Fundamental Laws of the Land: or thirdly, you are to draw a line of vanity over this your Proposal, as not reaching the <hi>Heights and Depths, the Lengths and Breadths of that Good Old Cause,</hi> the declared end of your Engagements. Or lastly, You may, with trembling, expect that the faithful and onely wise God, who is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming Fire, and whose Eyes have seen the Designes and Outgoings of your souls from <hi>Naseby</hi> hitherto, will sooner or later, powre out contempt upon your Heads, and judge you as men that break <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and religious Vows</hi> are judged.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But upon what side soever this Proposal is to be taken, it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me that, as it proceedeth from you, the honourable <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Army,</hi> it will be charged through with this ensuing <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma;</hi> either it wills that none but those whose Judgements are constituted according to the Rules therein expressed, should be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and protected in their professions with the protection of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59153:16"/> Commonwealth; or else that those who are of another Constitution, should act in their own behalf, as the Council of Officers hath, by this, done in theirs. If in the former way, Then the foregoing and the following Arguments, in this Discourse, rise up both against it, and them. If in the later, where is that publickness of spirit, which the Authors of this Tender, once professed to be in them, by enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for the Liberties of all the free-born people of the Land, as well as for their own?</p>
            <p n="9">9. If we may not call this <hi>Liberty,</hi> thus extended as the present Debate contends to have it, the indubitable <hi>Right</hi> of the People; yet at the least it cannot but be doubtful to <hi>All</hi> that have any minde to question things before they credit them, and become a Scruple to men of Conscience (after all that which hath been urged, from time to time, in the behalf thereof) <hi>whether it be not the Right of Men.</hi> If it be so (and how it can be otherwise, I cannot possibly conceive) is it not far better, more suitable to the doubtful Conscience of the State, and much more likely to be well-pleasing to Jesus Christ, to erre upon the right hand of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> then upon the left hand of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity?</hi> Mercy rejoyceth over Judgement in the <hi>most High:</hi> How much more should those <hi>Gods of the World,</hi> who dwell in Houses of <hi>Clay,</hi> and whose <hi>Foundation</hi> is in the <hi>Dust,</hi> shew Lenity and Mercy and not Judgement, who have reason in abundance, at least to doubt whether they ought to spare or strike?</p>
            <p n="10">10. The loud Exclamations of an accursed Toleration, (for so some zealous men do phrase it, who know not what spirit they are of) are not much to be observed in this Case, and at this time of <hi>Settlement,</hi> (except it be for the rebuke of that unclean and fiery spirit from whence they proceed) nor will the Parliament, or Army, I presume, be driven by such blasts to do or settle any thing, to the just complaint of any party whatsoever. For if Successes be any Decisions of things in Controversie, or Determinations of the Righteousness or Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness of a Cause or Quarrel (and there is some notice to be taken of a <hi>continued Line</hi> or <hi>Series</hi> of them) the Lord of <hi>Hosts</hi> hath (as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, so) even now determined between the Presbyterian claim (in conjunction with the Royal Party) and that sort of men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sectaries: and from this there is a new Argument to be raised and urged in the behalf of their Liberty. Their uniting together for the Maintenance and Defence of the Cause of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, against them that rose up to invade it, is a passage of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuce, not lightly to be passed over. They stood up joyntly for the Rights and Liberties of the Nation in general, (in which their own
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59153:17"/> are included) and became instrumental in their measures for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof from the danger threatned; and for the safeguard of that Government, from which they do now expect their protection. Is it just or prudent to withhold from them the Fruit of their Labors, which the good hand of Providence hath made to grow up for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon use? shall these, or any of these, be saved and preserved (through Divine Goodness) from the violence of the <hi>Common Adversary,</hi> that looked with a rough countenance upon the whole, to receive blows and wounds in the house of <hi>their Friends,</hi> from whom they have reason and assurance given to hope for better entertainment? You may be pleased to consider from whom those Exclamations, mentioned in the beginning of this Section, do break out; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom they do sparkle in their rage of fire; and then judge.</p>
            <p n="11">11. When that free and publick Spirit, that Spirit of Ingenuity, Righteousness and Moderation, wherewith you were acted in dayes of Old, cometh up into our Remembrance and Consideration, we cannot but wonder at this Proposal; and suppose that there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Root nor Branch, Head nor Foot of the Minde or Desire of the Council of Officers therein; but rather, that it is the spurious and unhappy production of some distempered Spirit, begotten in the night, and imposed on You. For into whose Thoughts can it enter, that an Army that hath contended for <hi>Religious Liberty</hi> so many years in Blood, and have made the Foes of the said Liberty, how great and authoritative soever they have appeared, to become their <hi>Footstool,</hi> should give away with their own hands, wittingly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking, that Liberty, or at least, a very great part thereof, which hath cost them so dear, and is the Price of the Lives of so many Men of Honour and Renown, which have fallen in the Purchase? At such a thing as this, the Heavens would be astonished, and the Earth confounded, should it not be held and esteemed by Men of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, amongst those <hi>Monstra Horrenda,</hi> those dreadful and mishapen Monsters, which Nature is ashamed to own. A perswasion that this work is yours, could not have the least room in us who are Lookers on, and Observers of you, had you not given it under your Hands, and held it up to the view of the World in Print: nay, we cannot be so confident now, neither, that we see the Heart and Soul of the Armies Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncil therein; because some of you have wished that <hi>that Proposal had not been born,</hi> (at least in that form in which it now seeth the light) and others, that it had not been printed; so unwilling have some among your selves, who are more tender of your Name, Cause and Honour, been, that your Nakedness should not appear. It is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59153:17"/> then, vehemently to be suspected (from divers grounds of guesse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides these two) that you have been imposed upon, in this your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking; and that you have not used your own Eyes▪ nor your own Reason, nor your own Judgements, nay, nor your own Wills; but by a strange cessation of these Arms upon your side, you have suffered the Judgement and the Will of <hi>one Magisterial Doctor,</hi> to triumph over you and yours, and to sit down in the Chair. Alas! Gentlemen, could you not see that that Doctor had a new Device and Designe? The Charge which he gave upon the <hi>Socinian</hi> Party with his Quill, being, even in the Judgement of the Learned and more sober of his <hi>own side,</hi> but weak; and so not likely to gain that Honour to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizer, as might be expected; nor to put his Adversaries to the Rout. He wheeles off from that kinde of service, and endeavours to pitch his Tent amongst your Tents, and to engage the Parliament and Army in his Quarrel; <hi>That what he could not do with his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they may (if possible) do with their Swords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. For it is (indeed) bruited abroad amongst some, for a Truth, that one Finger at least, (if not the whole Head, and both the Hands) of Doctor <hi>John Owen,</hi> was in the compiling and drawing up of this Proposal. The Materials, I confess, and the compacting of them together, do shew the Doctor; and the Doctor in them sheweth himself a man, led (not by that Spirit of Truth which was with <hi>Paul,</hi> in his laying down that Article of Justifying Faith to the believing <hi>Romans,</hi> cap. 10. 9. nor by that Spirit of Sweetness, which the Nature and Form of Independency recuires, but) by the Spirit of him (<hi>Athanasius</hi> I mean) who made the deepest Mysteries, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as they are notioned by him, the Objects of saying Faith; and damned all that could not believe them: yet we finde not that he (did, as this Doctor hath done) removed such as dissented from his <hi>Creed,</hi> out of the countenance and protection of State. And seeing Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> (if Reports abuse him not) hath had the greatest share in this performance, let him observe, that if he please to maintain the Cause of his narrow-chested Toleration, and to shew the grounds of its contraction, I dare presume (because there are so many, who are express and clear for perfect Liberty) he will not want an Adversary to combate with him: But if none of these should arise to plead the Cause of an Interest so much mistaken and despised, as this of <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> is, some Stone, at length, will speak, rather then he shall go off without encounter. But this by the way. Be advised, ye sons of Honour and Esteem, to take heed how you gratifie the will of one particular Interest or sort of Men, against the Just Rights and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59153:18"/> of more then one; there being nothing more prejudicial to a Kingdom or a Commonwealth, then to advance one Party of Faction to the just discontent of all the rest.</p>
            <p n="13">13. But if (notwithstanding all probabilities, yea, and this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil's own <hi>Old Tenders,</hi> to the contrary) it must be accepted for the <hi>Proposal of the Officers of the Army:</hi> then, Gentlemen, I beseech you have a little more patience with me, while I expostulate with you, and reason further thereupon; and that too, with respect of that Liberty for which you petition in the behalf of your selves: Either, you desire it as your Right and Due; or as that which you would have conferred upon you meerly out of the Grace and Favour of the Parliament: if you move, in this part of your Address, upon the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Foot of Account, then the Parliament, if they please, may deny your Request, and yet do you no wrong in their denial. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is, Because that which proceeds out of the meer <hi>Beneplacitum,</hi> the good Will and Grace of the Giver, cannot be challenged upon any other Terms then the Promise, (if there be any) of the Donor for the making of such a Vouchsafement: where I owe nothing, I am not bound to make payment. Have the High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bound themselves by <hi>Promise</hi> to grant Liberty, together with their protection and encouragement, to the Men of your Character and Qualification? If your Motion herein be upon the former; that is, If Liberty for Men of your Judgement be your Right, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you petition to have it confirmed and settled upon you, then it remains for you to shew, that those left out by you, to be chased by the Spirit of Violence, have forfeited their Right of Liberty; or else that they have no right to such a Freedom, neither by the Law of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, nor by the Fundamental Law of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="14">14. It may be concluded, I suppose, without any violence offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this Proposal, that the minde and purpose of it is, That those who are not of the same minde in all things with it, should be left to the Parliament, to be proceeded against as Malefactors, they being in the Judgement of the Petitioners, unworthy of any better Usage. Why? what is their Crime? their Crime is, Their Consciences will not give them leave to believe such things as the Proposal speakes of; and therefore, they must be interdicted the use of their Liberty (<hi>ipso facto</hi>) and be dealt withal as capital Offenders. Herein you pre-sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of this world, and consequently, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. have a lawful Jurisdiction over the Conscience, and an unquestionable Authority to exercise <hi>Coercive power</hi> over Men, barely for their Opinion about
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59153:18"/> things, more especially, pertaining to God. This was not alwayes the Judgement of the Officers of the Army; or if it were, your proceeding in the Eighth Article of your Draught of an Agreement of the People (which we have often noted) was most intolerable; In which Article, you confine and tie up the People Representatives (there intended for the <hi>Supreme Judicatory</hi>) from extending their power to things <hi>Spiritual or Evangelical.</hi> Now in prosecution of your then Judgement, I doubt not but it may be made appear in clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of light, That <hi>the</hi> Parliament, (<hi>or any secular Powers of the world) hath no power</hi> (de Jure) <hi>settled in them, to make or enact any Law, or to put in Execution any Law made, for the constraining of any of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to be of this or that Minde or Way, in Doctrine, or in the worship of God.</hi> (I say not, but that they may hold out a Confession of Faith, according to the best of their Understanding in the Gospel of Jesus Christ, and imploy men able and well qualified, for the teaching of the Nation, and to win men to imbrace the Faith of God, and encourage such men by all due means in the performance of their Work: what I therefore assert, is, <hi>That they ought not to exercise any coercive power over Men, barely for their dissent in points of Faith, or for thinking otherwise then the publick Profession of the Nation speaks.</hi>) And this, I hope, will be evinced in the following Periods: yet with a full reserve of all humble and due Respects and Confessions of Honour and Observance to that Supreme Court.</p>
            <p n="15">15. We have before observed, that men obtain the place of Trust and Rule over their Brethren, Either by a divine and immediate <hi>Consecration,</hi> or <hi>by Conquest,</hi> or <hi>by the Consent</hi> and <hi>Choice</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, over whom they are to rule. The first way is run out long ago. The second is more brutal, and seldom pleaded or insisted on by the <hi>Ruler,</hi> because it promiseth little lasting peace or safety to his Throne. The third way appeares with the face of a man upon it, and is humane and rational. The Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. obtain their Power and Jurisdiction in and over the great and weighty Affaires of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> by <hi>the Choice</hi> and <hi>Approbation of the people,</hi> by whom, and for whose benefit they are entrusted, (this is that which is of so catholick or general a confession and acknowledgement, that it stands in need of no further proof to make it an acceptable and established Maxime or Rule of State) and the power which they have, is derived to them, and descends upon them, from the people. Now it is most clear, That the people cannot be interpreted to have any will, in passing away this power to, and setling of it in, the Parliament, that they should extend and exercise it to the decreeing and inflicting of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59153:19"/> punishments on them; in case their Consciences shall not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded about things of Religion, as the Conscience of the Parliament is. For suppose that every Individual person, who hath given his voice for the chusing of Parliamant-men, should be examined upon this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory; whether he intended, in giving his voice, that those Men so chosen by him, should (if they should be so inclined) make penal Statutes for the constraining of him to be of this or that minde in points of Faith or Divine Worship; or, which is all one, for the taking away of the Liberty of his Conscience from him? Do you think that the answer to be given hereto, would not be in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and that you should hear him speaking thus, or to this effect: <hi>I desire to serve and worship God, according to the light and Dictates of my Conscience, and not to be deprived of my Liberty therein?</hi> If this, then, be the return which every individual of the people will make to such a Demand, (as most certain it is, except those who are yet to chuse their Religion, and are contented that the Parliament should be their chusers, to save themselves the trouble of chusing; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of which sort of men is not to be heeded, because they have no Conscience in these things: I say, If this be to be taken for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples answer to such a Demand) then the Parliament, who are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted by the people, and receive their power from them, cannot, by <hi>the Will of the people,</hi> extend their power to the inflicting of any civil punishments upon such as dissent from them in the things aforesaid, barely because they do dissent. Nor, secondly, would this be any part of the Authority of Parliament, if the will of the people should be to the conferring of such a power upon them: because no man hath any power or Authority, over the Conscience of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and so by consequence, hath no Authority to impower any, one or more, to execute such a kinde of Judgement, as this we sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k of: God having reserved the Dominion of Mens Consciences Himself and his Son Christ Jesus. Now because no man, nor Body of Men, can give or derive that unto another, of which he himself hath not the lawful power and possession, therefore it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that the Parliament hath no just or warrantable <hi>Authority,</hi> which derives it self from the people to them, by which they may lord over Mens Faith or Consciences, or endeavour to frame and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion their Judgements into their own or other mens likeness, by enacting and decreeing of punishments to be inflicted on such as cannot be molded into their Form of Confession.</p>
            <p n="16">16. If it should be said, in opposition to that which hath been now spoken, <hi>That the choice of the people doth give the Right to rule;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59153:19"/> but not the <hi>law of ruling by:</hi> so that the Magistrate being chosen, is not to have respect so much unto the peoples <hi>choice</hi> (or to their power in choosing) for the steerage of his power in <hi>Government,</hi> as to some other <hi>meanes</hi> for his Direction: unto this, answer way be given. First, That unto which this Objection, implicitely, supposeth the Magistrate should have recourse for the regulating, steering and extending of his power, must be a Rule given out for that purpose, either <hi>from God</hi> more immediately, or <hi>from Men.</hi> If the Rule be given more immediately <hi>from God;</hi> where is it? where may it be seen; that so the people also may have recourse to it, to receive sactisfaction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the extent of the <hi>power</hi> of their <hi>Rulers?</hi> As for the law of Moses delivered to the <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>people of Israel,</hi> how much that is concerned herein, we shall observe a little by and by. If this <hi>Rule</hi> for Government be from <hi>Men;</hi> it is either from the Magistrates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, who are to rule; or, from the subjects to be ruled: If from the Magistrates; then it is as much as if the Objection had said, The Law to rule and govern by, is the Rulers will and pleasure, and from this he is to fetch his Counsel and Direction for Government. But this was not wont to be born well. If from the people to be ruled, then that ground is kept, on which we stood before. But secondly, it is true; the <hi>choice of the people</hi> being strictly and formally considered, (and in that respect it gives <hi>Jus ad Regnum</hi>) doth not create or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Law by which the Magistrate must or ought to rule; but the <hi>Design</hi> and <hi>Intention</hi> of the people in their Choice, doth. Their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe is, That such as are chosen and entrusted by them, should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult and act for the preservation, benefit and advantage of the whole Community from which they have received that Trust and power: and the persons chosen, being men of Understanding, Reason and Judgement, are to make the <hi>lines</hi> of their Government to <hi>center</hi> in that <hi>point.</hi> The Law of Nature instructs and bindes men to study and take care for the things of their own safety and benefit: so that when they make choice of some to be Lords or Rulers over them, they must be understood to confer such a power upon them, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves (<hi>conjunctim &amp; divisim</hi>) have, from the said Law, to endeavour their own well-fare and prosperity: and what Princes or Parliaments who are entrusted by the People for their weal and safety, rule and govern by this Law of Nature, to this end; being chosen by the people, they may be said to be chosen by God; and ruling for their Subjects good, according to the Law of Nature (which is a certain and immoveable Bound and Limit to them, if there be no more set up) they may be also said, to rule by the Law of GOD, insomuch as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59153:20"/> that Great Creator is the Fountain of this Law.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Nor are the proceedings of the Kings and Governours of the Jews obligatory or binding to the Princes or Parliaments of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, so as that there is a necessity of following them: and this the <hi>Fathers of the Commonwealth</hi> acknowledge, by making Reason (not divine immediate <hi>Oracle</hi>) the Life of their Law; and by making choice onely of such Laws, from amongst those once in force with the Jews, which, in their Judgement, are consonant to Reason, and do hold correspondency with the end of all Government, <hi>vizt. The peoples Weal.</hi> So that the compulsive force which the Kings and Rulers of <hi>Israel</hi> used for the setting up of the Worship of the true God, and in demolishing Idols, is no warrantable ground for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of other Nations now, (how Pious and Christian soever they are) to proceed upon to the punishing of men, although of an erring Conscience, even in things of moment in Religion: For first, the Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> were strictly charged and required, under pain of divine displeasure, to rule according to the <hi>Book of the Law</hi> given by <hi>Moses:</hi> they were not left at Liberty, to govern according to their own wills; nor after the Reason or will of the State, but expresly by that Law; they must not turn to the <hi>Right Hand</hi> nor to the <hi>left.</hi> But by the Judgement and practice of our Law-Makers, and Law-Expositors, (as hath been said) Princes or Parliaments are not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to tread exactly in the steps of those Laws of <hi>Moses;</hi> but are left at their Liberty to chuse or to refuse what of them, they (upon Reason's Information) shall see good. But further, and in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, The Monarchy of the Jews is expired (in the letter and formality thereof) and not descended or derived down to any the Nations or Commonwealths of the world beside: nor is it preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Rulers of this Nation, that they are the undoubted Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors of the Kings of the Jews, and do rise up after Them to sit upon their <hi>Throne,</hi> and to act by their Law. Thirdly; This Kingdom of Israel was figurative of that Dominion and Soveraignty which the Lord Jesus was to receive and exercise over the world; more especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, over his own Church and people. So that what was done by the Kings of Israel, cannot (<hi>eo nomine,</hi> or because done by Them) be taken as binding to the <hi>Princes of the Nations,</hi> to do the <hi>Things</hi> aforesaid. Fourthly; God vouchsafed to the Kings and Princes of Israel, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of his own making, and other meanes for inquiry in doubtful cases; and by these they were many times directed what they should do. Fifthly, In the giving of the law to Israel, there was not the least word or Intimation given, that the Kings of the Nations which then
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59153:20"/> were, or which after should be, should observe the same Course and Rule for Governing in their Dominions, which were commanded to be observed within the gates of Israel. Sixthly, and lastly; If Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Governours or <hi>the Princes of the Nations</hi> conceive themselves bound to govern by the law of <hi>Moses</hi> in one part thereof, why not in all, and every part? there being nothing delivered whereby they may conceive themselves obliged to the observation of some part thereof, and set at freedom from the rest. But of what an unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant sound this is in the ears of Men acquainted with any thing of publique concernment, and how repugnant to the Gospel of Christ Jesus, there is no need that any notice should be given.</p>
            <p n="18">18. If it be questioned why the Magistrates Jurisdiction over the Consciences of his subjects should not be held as acceptable and as well-pleasing to God now, as it was in the time of the <hi>Law;</hi> it may be answered: first; It is not so clear that the governours of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Israel</hi> had any such Jurisdiction or Authority conferred upon Them by that law. But secondly; let the Authority of <hi>these</hi> be whatsoever; it is most clear that it was derived to them from the Jehovah, in or by meanes of their Law-giver, <hi>Moses:</hi> so in like manner; when it shall be manifested That the Jehovah hath, by Son his Jesus, our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, ordained that the Magistrates of the Nations shall exercise Authority over the mindes and Consciences of their subjects, to constraine them to believe either as the Magstrates themselves, or any other sort or Interest of men besides them, do believe, by the infliction of such and such penalies; or That any one of those prime Ministers of the Gospel (the Apostles) hath appointed any Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates which were to succeed in the World to exercise any such kinde of Judgement upon those that are subjected under them; or given so much as the least intimation thereof; (<hi>actum erit de lite nostra</hi>) we will then lay down our Arms, and conclude, that there is some ground for the Rulers of this world to build upon, and to believe that such an Authority, and the execution thereof accordingly, is a work of acceptation with God: but because none of these things appear, the power spoken of comes deservedly under Question: and the Arm of any State may tremble to lift it self up to the doing of any thing of that kinde. We may adde to this; thirdly, That the Bosome of Government amongst the Jews, (as rigid and severe as it is thought to have been) was not so narrow and contracted, but that it received men of divers wayes, and of very different apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions about divine things, with patience, and into protection. Those that have observed and written of their Customs and Antiquities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59153:21"/> us, that there were many Sects among them. They had and protected their <hi>Proselytes of the gates</hi> (Observers of <hi>Noahs</hi> Precepts onely) as well as their <hi>Proselytes of the Temple:</hi> there were the <hi>Esseni,</hi> men of a very severe life, but superstitious minde▪ The <hi>Pharisees,</hi> exceedingly addicted to Traditions (or humane Additions:) and the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who denied the doctrine of the Resurrection from the dead, and the existence of Angels and Spirits. All these (and more then these) lived and enjoyed their Liberty under that Government. And in their receiving of <hi>Proselytes,</hi> we finde them very careful to search into the Principles of the desires of such, who had a minde to come <hi>over</hi> to them; to see that no apprehension of force or power, or any the like unnatural or unwarrantable means, did commit any rape upon them, whereby they might conceive a desire to adde <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves unto the Church of Israel.</hi> It is observed by <hi>Maimony,</hi> (and <hi>Ainsworth</hi> notes it out of him, on <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 12,) that the Judges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no Proselytes all the dayes of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is very notable; They would not in <hi>David</hi>'s dayes, lest they should have come of fear; nor in <hi>Solomons,</hi> lest they should have come because of the Kingdom and great prosperity which Israel then had. Would the Christian Kings and Governours of the Gentiles act in the same spirit, and walk by the same Rule; there would be no cause left, I conceive, for any to complain of force or coercive power, used by them, for the constraining of those over whom they rule, to be of one minde with themselves, in Points of Religion, and the Worship of GOD.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Jesus Christ, who is the <hi>onely Law-giver</hi> to his Church, gives this Precept for the regulating of the Conversations of his Disciples; <hi>Whatsoever you would that men should do to you, do ye even so to them.</hi> It will not be said, That a sitting down in the Throne of Government or place of Trust and Rule, doth exempt the Governours from the Observance of this Command. Well then; suppose the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> should be of a divers Opinion about the things of God: as for instance; suppose the Parliament should be of this minde, That Jesus Christ (who is yet the King of kings) is not the most High God; or (which is the same) that he is not co-equal and co-eternal with the Father; and that the People believe, as the Council of the Army speaks, in this Proposal, with which we are now conflicting. What should the Parliament do in this Case? If they make a Law, in favour of the Peoples Judgement, against their own, then they wrong themselves; and it is believed they will not do so. If they enact a penal Law in favour of their own Opinion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59153:21"/> against the people; then, besides the injury which they do the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they violate and trample upon that <hi>Royal Law</hi> before mentioned, and thereby become guilty before the great <hi>Tribunal of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. It is of very dangerous consequence for any persons or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers, to disparage the glorious Gospel of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, with weakness and insufficiency, for the management of its own affairs amongst men. What do the secular Governments of this world do less, when they intermingle their power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with the things of God, and Gospel of Christ? do they not thereby declare and pronounce, That the Laws of Jesus Christ are weak of themselves, and unable to supplant Error? or that they are defective, and have need of some supplement of their making and contrivance, to serve in the place of that which is wanting? and therein are so far from attributing incomparable Wisdom to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof, which is His due; that they reflect upon Him, with fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and improvidence. The great Jehovah wills not that men should imploy their humane <hi>Arts of Addition</hi> or <hi>Substraction,</hi> about his things. And it was <hi>Agurs</hi> counsel to his Scholar, That he should not <hi>adde to the words of God,</hi> (and he gives this reason) <hi>lest he reprove thee, and thou art found a lyar,</hi> i. e. lest he correct thee with his Rod, who by thy addition, hast blemished the reputation of his Word. Did God take so much care that imperfection should not be charged upon his Law, which is the less; and shall we think He will take it kindly, or patiently indeed, that his Gospel, which is as the Sun for glory of Wisdome, should be called in question for insufficiency, by the additions of <hi>humane Acts and Ordinances? Be wise therefore, Oh ye Kings; and be instructed, you that are Judges of this earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. That most excellent Author of that Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> saith thus, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. 2. That <hi>He</hi> (Jesus Christ) <hi>was faithful to Him</hi> (the Father) <hi>that appointed him; as also Moses was faithful in all his house. Moses</hi> is said to be faithful for this Reason, (amongst other;) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he, being appointed by Jehovah, a Law-giver to the people of <hi>Israel,</hi> delivered and gave in charge <hi>all such things,</hi> as were needful to the regulating of the Affairs (whether Ecclesiastical or Civil) of that Nation; by means whereof, he hath obtained this Honour, to be recorded <hi>faithful.</hi> Now either Jesus Christ hath not been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his <hi>House,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> was in his; or else he hath left an express <hi>Commission</hi> under hand and seal, requiring and authorizing all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Migistrates to take upon them the Government over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of their subjects, and to punish them if they will not believe his <hi>Gospel;</hi> or if they shall believe in any part thereof, otherwise then
<pb facs="tcp:59153:22"/> the truth indeed is: or else such an intermedling of the Magistrate is no way requisite or needful; but rather highly displeasing to this Supreme Law-giver; inasmuch as it doth, upon the matter, charge him with <hi>unfaithfulness,</hi> and therein set Him far beneath his Servant <hi>Moses. Kiss the Son, lest he be angry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. The Sum &amp; Conclusion of all is this, That the Civil Magistrates are authorized neither by the will of the <hi>People</hi> who choose them, nor from any power the <hi>People</hi> have for such a purpose, nor by any word or Commission from <hi>God</hi> or his Son Jesus Christ, to make or ordain any Lawes for the constraining of men to believe as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, or to worship as they worship: and consequently, that they have no Authority at all to imploy themselves in the Execution of any such workes.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Hence may the Princes of this World (by whatsoever name they are called and dignified) be advertised to take heed of coming too neare that <hi>mount,</hi> which the Jehovah hath sanctifyed for <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> and <hi>his Son Jesus</hi> to set their Thrones in. I am for the peace and settlement of the Nations; and would that they should be setled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such a <hi>Bottom,</hi> that it may stand with the good liking of God, till He shall please to call in the <hi>Commissions</hi> of all the Kings and Rulers of this Earth, and discharge Them from any further attendance and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of that kinde; But I verily believe, that if any stone in our Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, now intended to be laid, be set upon any part of those Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which he hath more especially reserved for Himself and his Christ, He will very suddenly scatter it with the whirle-wind of his anger and indignation; and thereby shew the vanity of the Builders, and give them a late occasion to repent of their rashness; when they shall see their Endeavours laid waste, and themselves or their Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities cast out into sufferings. Yet if (notwithstanding the serious fore-thoughts of these things) they shall proceed, upon their own Accounts, to the Arraignment of men, because their Judgements do not jump with the Judgement of the State, who go about to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure by their Authority; the prosecuted (although erring in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) may <hi>traverse</hi> the whole proceeding with Pleasure and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, on this Ground, that they stand <hi>coram non-Judice;</hi> and in their Hearts may appeal to a <hi>Higher,</hi> and the <hi>proper Judge,</hi> even to <hi>Jesus, the Lord of quick and dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. But why do I reason so pensively concerning the power of our great <hi>Court of Parliament;</hi> as if they were about to do any thing unworthy Themselves, and that great Trust with which the people have invested them? No; I hope there are so many <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liels</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59153:22"/> in that Council, that they will not proceed to censure men of a divers mind from theirs in the doctrines of Faith or Worship, lest they should be found, by the grand and most righteous inquisition of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men fighting against God: Or if they are so confident of their own present apprehensions, about things of that nature, as not to believe they may be mistaken; yet their Wisdom, after the observation of so many (&amp; those so various) Passages of divine Providence, is so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, that they will take heed how they usurp any part of the Crown of Jesus Christ our King, who alone hath the Legislative power over the conscience, (as it hath been often intimated.) Dissenting men, who all of them united and rose up to ingage in the behalf of the present Authority, against the late Adversary, may be confident, I presume, that they shall not be denied the <hi>Cause of their Ingagement,</hi> by this Parliament. It remains, then, that that High Court be most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly desired that they would settle things so, that no following powers may easily invade our Christian Liberty (for who knoweth what disposition they will be of, that shall arise after them?) and that they and you, (the Noble Officers of the Army) would take all care to benefit your own, and our Posterities, and to commend your Names to be imbalmed by them for perpetuity, through the Remembrance of your most just and righteous Actions, and happy Endeavours for <hi>Publique Settlement.</hi> That night wherein no man can work, comes on apace upon you, as upon all the world: It will not be long, before Death set up his Ensignes of Conquest and Triumph over you, and lay you in the Dust, and shut you up as Prisoners unto the exact and most impartial <hi>Judgement of the great day;</hi> when you, as well as those who now are under you, must appear before the <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> of the Lord: at which time, the remembrance of those <hi>Acts</hi> which have been past, and Works done by you out of a sincere heart, to the breaking of every Yoke of Oppression, &amp; to the easing of the Conscience of every man, professing Jesus Christ, from all unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Impositions, will administer more true Consolation to you, and bring in more honour and rejoycing, then whatsoever you have done out of a private spirit, or with a design to gratifie one sort of men, to the just grievance of all: These, and the like works or intentions to these, should you be guilty of them any further, (which God avert) being of a Demerit, which (under the Righteous Judgement of God) is able to sink your souls into Eternal Darkness, and to pierce them through with ten thousand sorrows.</p>
            <p n="25">25. But why, (O Magnanimous and Religious Officers) why have you tempted that <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> and laid a snare, and a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59153:23"/> stumbling block in the way to the settlement of the just Rights and Liberties of the People? do you not know that <hi>Dominion</hi> is, of it self a sore Temptation? how much sorer then, when the <hi>Sons of that Dominion</hi> shall be provoked to exceed those Bounds which God hath set up to them, by Tenders and Proposals offered from such Hands as <hi>Yours?</hi> Do you think that Parliaments are as God, that can be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by none; that you have so easily, in one Proposal, given away (as far as in you lieth) the <hi>Good Old Cause,</hi> which is your <hi>Cause,</hi> and the Parliaments <hi>Cause,</hi> and the <hi>Cause</hi> of every honest and religious Man in the Nations under their Government? For what you leave to Parliaments, as that you would have to fall under their cognizance now, may be a leading Case, and a means to render even your selves obnoxious to their censures for your Judgements, in what you differ from them, another day; because your selves, and such as you, may be proceeded against, upon as just and warrantable grounds, if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parliament please, as those are, on which you do, in effect, move <hi>This</hi> to proceed against others; and so you (yea, and the Members of this present Parliament also) may lose your Liberty by a Law of your own making, upon the matter. Be it far from you, then, (honoured and Christian Brethren) to tempt any unto evil; much less your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the Creators of your Power and Authority. Nay, you should be so far removed from a work of that dismal and horrid nature, that if you discovered a Temptation likely to arise amongst Them, or to be offered to them by any hand whatsoever, you should give timely notice, that they may beware, and use all means meet and possi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le; that they may not stain their Glory with any Action of a dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and unworthy note. Thus did our <hi>Lord</hi> to his Apostle <hi>Peter;</hi> He should have been your Example. Oh! why have you not done thus?</p>
            <p n="26">26. Time was, when the Soul of the Army took pleasure in the spirit of Moderation and Forbearance; witness their commendation of some Tracts, which have been, at sundry times, published in favour of that Liberty for which this Discourse hath travelled. Have you not lost very much of that<note place="margin">
                  <p>Zeal examined, <hi>&amp;c. Read also</hi> A discourse of the Peace of the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Milton'<hi>s Civil power in Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>siastical Causes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Spirit, in propounding as you have done; and thereby leaving some out for a prey, to whom things, which you say, you see, are not so clear; whose Consciences, are yet very tender of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any thing of this nature, which is not with some considerable clearness proposed in the Scriptures? Let not that Christian Moderation and Forbearance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59153:23"/> which once filled the Hearts of many of you, be converted and sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into rigidness, harshness and cruelty. The Lord is at hand, who is the Judge.</p>
            <p>Be advised at last (you men of might and strength, whom God hath honoured) to consider <hi>Seven times</hi> what you ought to do in this great business of <hi>Christian Liberty.</hi> Let your own wisedom, your Names and Honours, <hi>move</hi> you to consider. Let the <hi>remembrance</hi> of the <hi>good Old Cause,</hi> which you are now raised up again (by the good providence of God) to assert and contend for, <hi>move</hi> you. Let the wrath of the Lamb which will be provoked by pressing too near his Throne with a bold spirit of Usurpation, <hi>move</hi> you; and let the humble Admonitions of your faithful friends, who dare not flatter you in any unrighteous worke; yet have it in their hearts to own and honour you as much as any whose dwellings are below, <hi>move</hi> you to revise your Proposal, and to consider what you have done therein. Let not that respect which you bear to any single Interest or sort of men, biass your affections so strongly, as to cause you to beare too hard upon the natural Rights of others, for whose Liberty also you are bound by your own Engagements to endeavour. I will trouble you no further, but only to tell you, that the fore-apprehensions of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing esteemed an Advocate for the Socinian party, do not much stick with me. I can profess freely and with a good Conscience before God, Angels and men, that I have had a greater Eye upon the <hi>Doctrine of Liberty▪</hi> in this discourse, then upon the <hi>Liberty</hi> of any particular <hi>Doctrine</hi> whatsoever; and should have as much to say in the behalfe of <hi>Calvinisme</hi> (or any other Religious Sect) in respect of <hi>Toleration,</hi> were it likely that that should be forced to lye under the <hi>Altar</hi> of this kinde of suffering; as for this Interest, which by your meanes hath had occasion to complaine and speake. The Lord give this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and this Army wisedom in <hi>this their day,</hi> to finde out and pitch upon such solid Grounds and Principles as may make for the firm settlement of their own and the Nations <hi>Peace and Liberty.</hi> And seeing by the wise dispose of our God, who is to be blessed for ever, and who ruleth in the Heavens, and doth what pleaseth Him in the Kingdoms of this World, that things are brought to such an Issue at present <hi>that they may do what they will;</hi> Let it be their part and study, neither to will nor to endeavour the <hi>Doing</hi> of any more <hi>then what they may,</hi> with respect to the Lawes of God and Nature. The time is drawing on apace wherein the Heavens shall be no more; at which time you, and all the secular powers and potentates in the World,
<pb facs="tcp:59153:24"/> must bow down, and yeeld up your Accompts before<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the highe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Tribunal. As it is your wisdom, then, whiles you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your fraile Tabernacles, and have to do with the difficult <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>faires of this World, to direct your steps in such a straight course and line, that when you shall depart the Stage of <hi>publique Action,</hi> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay receive a <hi>bene discessit</hi> from Him who is the supreme Moderator of the Universe, and may enjoy the inestimable happiness and blessing of a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>quiet Conscience:</hi> so shall it be my prayer to the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> in your behalfe, that when He, whom the <hi>Heaven of Heavens must contain untill the time of the restitution of all things, shall come riding upon the Clouds of Heaven,</hi> to the Judgement of the World; You may be able to render an Accompt of your Transactions, in these hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Affairs, with Joy, and not with Grief.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Septem. 22. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully devoted to serve you in any just Interest.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59153:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>